## MANOJ KUMAR

+1(248) 854-8669

Manhojkummar@gmail.com ♦ LinkedIn ♦ Website ♦ Github

#### **SUMMARY**

Data Science and Machine Learning Engineer professional specialized in Data Analysis, Statistical Analysis & Modelling, Time Series Analysis & Modelling, Machine Learning, Deep Learning and Natural Language Processing (NLP) across retail, aerospace, and finance industries. Currently on a CPT Visa with allowed work of 40 hours per week.

#### **EDUCATION**

M.B.A in Technology and Data Science, Walsh College, Michigan

Apr 2021 - Expected Sep 2022

Coursework: Design Thinking, Marketing, Managerial Accounting.

P.G Diploma in Machine Learning & Artificial Intelligence, I.I.I.T B, India

Dec 2019 - Dec 2020

Coursework: Statistics, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Deep Learning, Reinforcement Learning

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Science, B.M.S Institute of Technology, India

Sep 2012 - Sep 2016

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages Python, SQL (T-SQL), R

Data Science Statistical Analysis and Modelling, Time Series Analysis and Modelling,

Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Clustering, Regression, Classification, Descriptive & Inferential Statistics, A/B Testing,

Funnel & Causal Analysis, Survival Analysis & Modelling, Interpretable M.L/A.I

Cloud Platforms

Google Cloud Platform(GCP), Amazon Web Services(AWS) and Microsoft Azure

Spark (Python, Scala), Hive and Data Build Tool

Data Processing

Spark (1 ython, Scala), Three and Data Bund To

BigQuery, Snowflake, Amazon S3, Teradata

Visualization & Reporting Tableau, Dash, RShiny, Seaborn, ggPlot, Matplotlib

MLOps Github, MLFlow, DVC, EvidentlyAI, Metaflow, Seldon

Other Tools Apache Hadoop, Apache Airflow, Databricks, RAPIDS(cuDF, cuML)

Amazon Sagemaker, Azure Data Factory, Docker, Kubernetes, FastAPI, MongoDB

#### EXPERIENCE

# Data Scientist Walmart Labs

Oct 2019 - May 2021

Bengaluru, India

- Built a Markdown Optimizer using Statistical Modelling and Machine Learning for capturing Price Elasticity and Forecasting to predict weekly demand of 60 million SKUs across countries.
- Researched, experimented, and constructed time series models to best capture patterns for intermittent time series and cluster similar time series using global features such as wavelet transforms, item features, pricing etc.
- Built statistical models using constrained regression to capture price elasticity and forecasting models using tree-based ensembles with comprehensive feature engineering.
- Improved forecasting performance by 27% (sMAPE) on an average across countries.
- Constructed and performed A/B Experiments for testing across departments and countries for deploying statistical/forecasting models.
- Reduced computational time by 70% (10 hours to 3 hours) by using distributed computation i.e UDFs on Spark to optimize computational resources. Was awarded with the SPOT award for my contribution.
- Constructed and streamlined end-to-end data pipelines with integrated MLOps principles utilizing Data/Model Governance, Code/Data/Model Versioning using open source tools.

- Collaborated with business stakeholders for capturing product requirements, sketched product roadmaps, understood market-specific nuances and helped adopt the product in 5 countries with an adoption rate of 60-70% replacing a third-party product which resulted in saving about \$30 million in markdown sales
- Built customer insights product for capturing Walmart's store concerns like COVID mask concerns, parking space, long queues etc using tweets from Twitter. Automated classification of tweets to concerns using NLP transformers like BERT, RoBERTa etc. Also, built a Tableau dashboard for the customer team to provide insights into major concerns in stores in the USA.

Data Scientist
Network International LLC

Mar 2019 - Jun 2019

Dubai, United Arab Emirates

• Built a churn model with churn risk prioritization for each acquiring merchant based on the transactional, demographic, product cross-selling data and made it available to the RM's through a Dash dashboard resulting in data-driven churn prevention by 30%.

• Consulted clients on using POS(Point of Sale) data to leverage smart decision making by analyzing and creating business intelligence reports in Tableau.

**Data Scientist** 

Mar 2018 - Mar 2019

Bengaluru, India

Rolls-Royce PLC

- Part of 12 member Data War Room in the Derby-United Kingdom, consisted of the best Data Scientists and Data Engineers across the company. The war room got recognition for its capabilities and achievements in providing data-driven decisions to solve business-critical problems.
- Performed root cause analysis to explore avenues of probable causes and key drivers impacting the blade life of Trent 1000 jet engine using Agile Data Science. Survival analysis for the reliability of engines in light of the failure events happening.
- Presented analysis and reports to the CEO and collaborated with engineers for in-depth analysis. These analyses were in turn given as recommendations to various airliners to reduce exposure to critical conditions.
- Researched the effect of volcanic ash on Trent 700 engine using flight path and volcanic cloud profiles and developed a risk model.
- Built a Market Intelligence product to capture trending news in the aerospace/aviation industry from different websites using python web scraping under ethical terms and automated creation of newsletters which was shared to the entire aviation division of the company every week reducing work of a team of 2.

Data Scientist

INSOFE

Jan 2017 - Mar 2018

Bengaluru, India

• Consulted for clients in the automobile, manufacturing and telecom industry in utilizing machine learning and statistics in solving business problems like causal inference, market segmentation, churn modelling, text classification etc.

### OTHER PROJECTS

#### Marketing Analytics - Freelancing

- Built Data Pipelines using Azure Data Factory, Databricks, Spark and Data Build tool for data processing of sales and media data from media agencies with automated data quality checks.
- Analysed the effect of campaigns on sales to make data-driven decisions on the advertising portfolio.

#### **ACHIEVEMENTS**

• First place in Walmart's LiveBetter Hackathon which was globally organized in 10 countries. Our solution was to tackle **optimum placement of electric charging stations across the USA** for converting the current Walmart fleet to Electric using Graph/Network Algorithms.

If not selected for this position, please give your feedback through this link which may take 2 seconds. This will be much appreciated.